Curriculum Vitae

CONTACT Information Swarup Ranjan Behera

Senior Data Scientist

Reliance Jio Platforms Ltd, Hyderabad

Phone: +91-9439872747 Email: swarup221b@gmail.com Web: LinkedIn, Personal Website

Research Interests I am interested in the research work related to machine learning, data mining, and application of these techniques. In particular *natural language processing* and *sport data mining*.

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati, Guwahati, India

Ph.D., Computer Science and Engineering, July 2015 - Sept 2021

- Thesis: Learning Player-specific Strategies Using Cricket Text Commentary.
- Supervisor: Dr. Vijaya Saradhi Vedula

M.Tech., Computer Science and Engineering, 7.99 CPI, July 2013 - June 2015

- Project: Spectral Clustering Using Convex and Constrained Settings.
- Supervisor: Dr. Vijaya Saradhi Vedula

Veer Surendra Sai University of Technology, Burla, Odisha, India

B.Tech., Computer Science and Engineering, 8.30 CPI, July 2008 - June 2012

- Project: A Novel Ontology Based Entity Relationship Model.
- Supervisor: Dr. Rakesh Mohanty

Experience

Reliance Jio Platforms Ltd, Hyderabad

Senior Data Scientist, Reliance Jio AI-CoE, Sept 2021 - Present

- Project: Sports, Call-center, and Bio-medical Speech and Text Analysis.
- Supervisor: Dr. Balakrishna Reddy P

Data Science Intern, Reliance Jio AI-CoE, June 2021 - August 2021

- Project: Sports and Call-center Text Processing and Analysis.
- Supervisor: Dr. Balakrishna Reddy P

PUBLICATIONS

- S. R. Behera and V. S. Vedula, Learning Strength and Weakness Rules of Cricket Players using Association Rule Mining, In proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Machine Learning and Data Mining for Sports Analytics (MSLA21), ECML/PKDD Workshop, Virtual, 2021.
- S. R. Behera, Performance Analysis of Batsman against Spin Bowling and Fast Bowling in Cricket, Ohio State Sports Analytics Association Conference (OSUSAAC20), Columbus, United States, 2020. (Best Research Award)
- S. R. Behera and V. S. Vedula, *Video Data Do More. Tracking Data Do Much. Text Commentary Data Do Much More*, Carnegie Mellon Sports Analytics Conference (CMSAC20), Pittsburgh, United States, 2020.
- S. R. Behera and V. S. Vedula, Stats Aren't Everything; Learning Strengths and Weaknesses of Cricket Players, In proceedings of the 7th Workshop on Machine Learning and Data Mining for Sports Analytics (MSLA20), ECML/PKDD Workshop, Ghent, Belgium, 2020.

- S. R. Behera and V. S. Vedula, *Mining Temporal Changes in Strengths and Weaknesses of Cricket Players Using Tensor Decomposition*, In proceedings of the 28th European Symposium on Artificial Neural Networks, Computational Intelligence and Machine Learning (ESANN20), Bruges, Belgium, 2020.
- S. R. Behera, P. Agrawal, A. Awekar and V. S. Vedula, *Mining Strengths and Weaknesses of Cricket Players Using Short Text Commentary*, 2019 18th IEEE International Conference On Machine Learning And Applications (ICMLA19), Boca Raton, FL, USA, 2019.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Spectral Clustering Using Convex and Constrained Settings: Proposed a framework that incorporates pairwise constraints into semidefinite spectral clustering. Extended it from passive learning to active learning and self-taught learning settings. Used Matlab. (Jul 2013 - Apr 2015, IIT Guwahati)

Virtual Learning Environment for Chemistry Department: Implemented an e-learning education system based on the web that models conventional inperson education by providing equivalent virtual access to classes, class content, tests, homework, grades, assessments. Used HTML, PHP, JavaScript, and MySQL. (May 2014 - Jun 2014, IIT Guwahati)

Community Detection Using Greedy Clique and Plex Algorithm: Implemented a community detection algorithm - Greedy Clique Expansion (GCE). Limitations of using GCE are identified and proposed an algorithm, Greedy Plex Expansion, a variant of GCE which uses plexes in place of cliques. Used C++. (Jan 2014 - Apr 2014, IIT Guwahati)

Web Search Engine: Built a web search engine that searches for 1.2 million webpages using the page-rank algorithm and suffix array data structure. Used Python, HTML, PHP, and JavaScript. (Jul 2013 - Dec 2013, IIT Guwahati)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, IIT Guwahati, July 2013 - Dec 2020

Database Lab	Spring-2015, Spring-2016, Spring-2020, Fall-2020	
Computing Lab	Spring-2017, Spring-2018, Spring-2019	
Software Engineering	Fall-2018, Fall-2019	
Design and Analysis of Alg	orithms Fall-2017	
Computer Vision using Ma	chine Learning Fall-2016	
Discrete Mathematics	Fall-2015	
Data Structures Lab	Fall-2014	
Probability and Linear Alg	ebra Spring-2014	
Data Communication	Fall-2013	

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, C

Statistical Tools: R

Computational Suite: MATLAB Database: MySQL, MongoDB

ML/DL/NLP Libraries: NumPy, SciPy, Scikit-learn, Pandas, TensorFlow, PyTorch,

NLTK, Gensim, transformers

Visualisation Tools: Matplotlib, Plotly, Gnuplot

Other Tools: R Shiny, Latex, Beamer, Microsoft Office, Inkscape

ACHIEVEMENTS

Grants and Fellowships

Grants and Fenowships		
• MHRD, Government of India Fellowship for PhD	July 2015 - June 2019	
• MHRD, Government of India Fellowship for MTech	July 2013 - June 2015	
• Odisha State Government Scholarship for BTech	July 2008 - June 2012	
National Rural Talent Scholarship	July 2001 - June 2004	

Academic

- Best research award at OSUSAAC 2020, Columbus, USA.
- All India rank 696 (99.68 percentile) in GATE 2013.
- Secured the third position in codezam, in Srujan 2011 at VSSUT, Burla.

Extra Curricular

- Organized Advaya 2015, PG cultural festival at IITG.
- Technical officer in the student gymkhana council 2014-2015 at IITG.
- Best departmental act award in Advaya 2014, PG cultural fest. at IITG.
- Gold medal for short movie-making in Film Festival 2012 at VSSUT, Burla.

COMMUNITY SERVICES Program Committee Member: ECML-PKDD 2020

Reviewer: IEEE VIS 2020, IEEE VIS 2021

Volunteer: ICVGIP 2016

References

Dr. Vijaya Saradhi Vedula, Ph.D

Associate Professor, Department of CSE Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati Guwahati, Assam, India 781039

saradhi@iitg.ac.in

Dr. Amit Awekar, Ph.D

Assistant Professor, Department of CSE Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati Guwahati, Assam, India 781039 amitawekar@gmail.com Dr. Ashish Anand, Ph.D

Associate Professor, Department of CSE Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati

Guwahati, Assam, India 781039

anand.ashish@iitg.ac.in

Dr. Rakesh Mohanty, Ph.D

Associate Professor, Department of CSE VSSUT Burla

Burla, Odisha, India 768018 rakesh.iitmphd@gmail.com